let's see two formulas for the sum of
the first n cubes the number I cubed can
be represented by an I by I by I cubical
stack of unit cubes so this stack
represents 1 cubed this one represents 2
cubed this one represents 3 cubed and so
on where we can end at n cubed in this
case we've pictured Nal 4 when we put
these Stacks together we see we have a
representation for the sum of the first
n positive cubes now if we lay out each
of the cubes flat each Cube forms an I
by I squ rectangle so the first Cube
forms a 1x1 rectangle the next one a 2x4
rectangle then a 3x9 rectangle all the
way down to the final one which forms an
N byn squ rectangle the first rectangle
represents the number one the second
rectangle represents the sum of the two
odd numbers 3 + 5 as shown here the
third rectangle represents the sum of
the odd numbers 7 + 9 + 11 so each of
these rectangles can be decomposed into
a sum of consecutive odd numbers the
last rectangle can be done so by
decomposing it into n * n -1 + 1 + n * n
-1 + 3 and so on up to n * n -1 + 2 N -
1 but this last number simplifies to n *
n + 1 -
1 from these rectangular diagrams then
we see that the sum of the first n
positive cubes is equal to the sum of
the odd integers starting from one and
ending at n * n + 1us 1 this formula is
amazing but we can use these rectangles
to say even more we can break each
rectangle into two separate rectangles
where one has dimensions and by the nth
triangular number we can take this
smaller rectangle rotate it and glue it
onto the other side of the rectangle
forming an L-shaped nomon in each Case
by construction these gons all fit
together perfectly to form a
square because because of the rectangle
Dimensions we see that this square has a
side length given by 1 + 2 up to n or
the sum of the first n positive integers
this means the total number of unit
cubes which was given by the sum of the
odd numbers from 1 to n * n + 1 - one
must also equal the square of the sum of
the first n positive integers but then
we can finish this off by connecting the
first and last formulas so that we see
that the sum of the first n positive
cubes must equ the square of the sum of
the first n positive integers this
formula is attributed to the ancient
Greek philosopher nomus the visual proof
we just presented is due to aleno Flores
but there are plenty of other visual
proofs of the same fact you can see
others on my Channel or you can find a
variety of them in Roger Nelson's books
proof without words volumes 1 2 and 3
have a look and let me know which visual
proof of nomiss theorem is your
favorite